Finding aid to the Women Ambassadors Oral History Project oral histories SSC.MS.00204
Sophia Smith Collection
Women Ambassadors Oral History Project oral histories
1916-2002
1980-1990
Sophia Smith Collection
Morin, Ann Miller
SSC.MS.00204
27 boxes (31 linear feet)
Collection consists mostly of oral histories conducted and collected by Morin of women ambassadors and state department employees, conducted in 1984, for her book, Her Excellency (1995). The collection also contains research files and typescripts of her book, Her Majesty, and a proposal and outline for a book, Madam Ambassador.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections. Collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use. Collection is stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advance notice. AV materials may not be viewed until in-house use copies are made.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ann Miller Morin donated this collection to the Sophia Smith Collection from 1998 to 2010.
Biographical / Historical
Ann Miller Morin, born 24 July 1924, was the wife of a Foreign Service Officer. She gathered information, including oral histories, from 36 "female chiefs of mission, from the first one appointed in 1933 to the 44th appointed in 1983." The Women Ambassadors Project resulted in a book entitled Her Excellency, published in 1995.
Other Finding Aids
This online finding aid currently provides detailed description of only some of the additions to this collection. Materials from accession 01S-23 are described in unpublished lists that can be sent to you upon request by contacting specialcollections@smith.edu
Scope and Contents
The collection consists mostly of oral histories conducted and collected by Morin of women ambassadors and state department employees, conducted in 1984, for her book, Her Excellency (1995). Included are interviews with Anne Armstrong, Jane Coon, Ruth Farkas, Millicent Fenwick, Jeane Kirkpatrick, Betty Dillon, Clare Booth Luce, Madeleine Albright, Jean Kennedy Smith, Mabel Smythe, Carol Laise, Margaret Tibbetts, Rozanne Ridgway, Anne Martindell, Constance Harvey, Nancy Ostrander, Mary Olmsted, Frances Willis, and Mari-Luci Jaramillo. The subject content of the interviews dates from circa 1933 to 1983. The collection also contains research files and typescripts of her book, Her Majesty, and a proposal and outline for a book, Madam Ambassador.
Women ambassadors--United States--Biography--Sources; Women diplomats--United States--Biography--Sources; United States--Foreign relations--1945-1989--Sources; Oral history--Archival resources; Morin, Ann Miller. Her Excellency -- Sources; Ambassadors; correspondence; Transcripts; Audiotapes; Oral histories; Motion pictures; photographs; memorabilia; Grant proposals; Books; Videotapes; Notes; clippings; Albright, Madeleine Korbel; Armstrong, Anne, 1924-; Black, Shirley Temple; Davis, Ruth; Donovan, Eileen; Fenwick, Millicent; Harvey, Constance; Kirkpatrick, Jeane J.; Luce, Clare Boothe, 1903-1987; Morin, Ann Miller; Ridgway, Rozanne; Smythe, Mabel M.; Tibbetts, Margaret Joy, 1919-; Watson, Barbara; Wells, Melissa; Whittlesey, Faith; Willis, Frances E.; Newberry, Suzanne Davis; Morin, Ann Miller
- Materials related to Women Ambassadors Project, Presidential Libraries Project, Foreign Service Family Oral History Projects, 1932-2002; 2003-S-0018
  - Materials related to Theresa Healy, 1986-2002; 2003-S-0018 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to Joan Clark, 1985-2002; 2003-S-0018 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to Ann Cox Chambers, 1985-1994; 2003-S-0018 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to Patricia Byrnes, 1976-1985; 2003-S-0018 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to Anne Forrester, 1979-1989; 2003-S-0018 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to Madeline Albright, 1997-2001; 2003-S-0018 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to Eugenie Anderson, 1949-1988; 2003-S-0018 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to Florence Jaffray Harriman, 1932-1995; 2003-S-0018 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to Clare Booth Luce, 1953-1996; 2003-S-0018 (Box 2)
  - Materials related to Ruth Bryan Owen, 1933-1987; 2003-S-0018 (Box 2)
  - Materials related to various ambassadors, 1986-1996; 2003-S-0018 (Box 2)
  - Materials related to Avis Bohlen, 1997-2000; 2003-S-0018 (Box 3)
  - Materials related to Elinor Constable, 1983-2002; 2003-S-0018 (Box 3)
  - Materials related Frances Cook, 1983-2002; 2003-S-0018 (Box 3)
  - Materials related to April Glaspie, 1990-2001; 2003-S-0018 (Box 3)
  - Materials related to Swanee Hunt, 1997-2001; 2003-S-0018 (Box 3)
  - Materials related to Mary Ryan, 2002; 2003-S-0018 (Box 3)
  - Materials related to various ambassadors, 1957-2002; 2003-S-0018 (Box 3)
  - Women Ambassadors Project correspondence, 1995-1998; 2003-S-0018 (Box 3)
  - Materials related to Presidential Libraries Project: Eisenhower Library, 1985-1991; 2003-S-0018 (Box 4)
  - Materials related to Presidential Libraries Project: Carter Library, 1986-1997; 2003-S-0018 (Box 4)
  - Materials related to Presidential Libraries Project: Ford Library, 1984-1988; 2003-S-0018 (Box 4)
  - Materials related to Presidential Libraries Project: Roosevelt Library, 1985-1996; 2003-S-0018 (Box 4)
  - Materials related to Presidential Libraries Project: Truman Library, 1984-1987; 2003-S-0018 (Box 4)
  - Materials related to Presidential Libraries Project: Nixon Library, 1987-1997; 2003-S-0018 (Box 4)
  - Materials related to Presidential Libraries Project: Johnson Library, 1985-1989; 2003-S-0018 (Box 4)
  - Notes, clippings, materials related to Presidential Libraries Project, 2002, undated; 2003-S-0018 (Box 4)
  - Ambassadors' staff lists, pay schedules, 1949-1998; 2003-S-0018 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous materials regarding ambassors, 1993-1998; 2003-S-0018 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and clippings related to Don Ritchie, Holsley Handeyside, 1988-1999; 2003-S-0018 (Box 4)
  - Various materials related to oral histories, 1981-1995; 2003-S-0018 (Box 4)
  - Smithsonian Institution: correspondence, notes, brochures, 1988-1990; 2003-S-0018 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and notes related to state historical and humanities associations, societies, 1988-1992; 2003-S-0018 (Box 4)
  - Women Ambassadors Project administrative files, 1985-1996; 2003-S-0018 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, notes related to Ann Miller Morin's "Her Excellency: An Oral History of American Women", 1995; 2003-S-0018 (Box 5)
  - Various materials related to Foreign Service Family Oral History Project, 1982, undated; 2003-S-0018 (Box 5)
  - Robin Holzhauer M.A. thesis: "Double Duty: The History and Changing Roles of Diplomatic Wives", 1995; 2003-S-0018 (Box 5)
  - Oral history transcript: Therese Healy, 2001; 2003-S-0018 (Box 5)
    General
  - Oral history transcript: Helene Von Damm, 1999; 2003-S-0018 (Box 5)
  - Oral history transcript: Eugenie Anderson, 1971; 2003-S-0018 (Box 6)
  - Oral history transcript: Ann Cox Chambers, 1985-1986; 2003-S-0018 (Box 6)
  - Oral history transcript: Frances Cook, 1986; 2003-S-0018 (Box 6)
  - Oral history transcript: Clare Booth Luce, 2001; 2003-S-0018 (Box 6)
- Biographical materials: Shirley Temple Black, Ruth Davies, Eileen Donovan, Jeane Kirkpatrick, Rozanne Ridgway, Barbara Watson, Melissa Wells, and Faith Whittlesey; and Ann Morin Miller project materials., 1965-2002; 2004-S-0071
  - Ambassador Barbara Watson: clippings, notes, oral listories, 1965-1997; 2004-S-0071 (Box 1)
  - Ambassador Barbara Watson: additional materials, undated; 2004-S-0071 (Box 2)
  - Ambassador Faith Whittlesey: oral history transcript, 2001; 2004-S-0071 (Box 2)
  - Ambassador Shirley Temple Black: clippings, correspondence, notes, undated; 2004-S-0071 (Box 2)
  - Videocassettes: Ambassadors Melissa Wells, Rozanne Ridgeway and Jeanne Kirkpatrick, 1987; 1988; 2004-S-0017 (Box 3)
  - Ambassador Ruth Davis: articles, clippings, correspondence, 1999-2001; 2004-S-0071 (Box 3)
  - Ambassador Eileen Donovan, 1985-2001; 2004-S-0071 (Box 3)
  - Women Ambassadors Project: files, correspondence, articles, notes, 1987-2002; 2004-S-0071 (Box 3)
- Materials related to Women Ambassadors Oral History Project, 1982-2002; 2010-S-0011; Morin, Ann Miller; 6.25 linear feet (5 boxes)
  Morin, Ann Miller
  - Card file boxes A-Z, undated; 2010-S-0011 (Box 1)
  - Card file box: Women Leaders - International Diplomacy, undated; 2010-S-0011 (Box 1)
  - Card file box: Women Power - Barbara Watson, undated; 2010-S-0011 (Box 1)
  - Card file boxes: interview cards, bibliography, undated; 2010-S-0011 (Box 1)
  - Address book, undated; 2010-S-0011 (Box 1)
  - Telephone logs, 1992-1994; 2010-S-0011 (Box 1)
  - Project proposals, 1989; 2010-S-0011 (Box 1)
  - Materials pertaining to Department of State conferences; correspondence; notebooks, 1985-1993; 2010-S-0011 (Box 1)
  - Reviews of book, "Her Excellency", 1994-1995; 2010-S-0011 (Box 2)
  - Ann Miller Morin lectures, circa 1995-1998; 2010-S-0011 (Box 2)
  - Release forms, photographs, publicity material, notes, 1982-2001; 2010-S-0011 (Box 2)
  - Transcripts and other project materials, circa 1980-1990; 2010-S-0011 (Box 2, Box 3)
  - Ann Miller Morin published articles, 1990-1999; 2010-S-0011 (Box 3)
  - Information regarding project participants, 1980-2002; 2010-S-0011 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and reports, 1980-1999; 2010-S-0011 (Box 4)
  - Publicity materials, 1990-1999; 2010-S-0011 (Box 5)
  - Materials regarding radio interviews, 1990-1999; 2010-S-0011 (Box 5)
  - Panels and conferences, 1997-2001; 2010-S-0011 (Box 5)
- Ann Miller Morin's research materials, correspondence, photographs, audio cassettes pertaining to women ambassadors, 1968-1998; 2016-S-0053; Morin, Ann Miller; 0.5 linear feet (1 box)
  - Research materials, correspondence, photographs regarding Melissa Wells, 1980-1999; 2016-S-0053 (Box 1)
  - Lecture, "U.S. Women Ambassadors," by Ann Miller Morin, 1988; 2016-S-0053 (Box 1)
  - Seventeen audiocassette interviews with Barbara Watson and others, 1968-1998; 2016-S-0053 (Box 1)
- Ann Miller Moran's notes, tapes, transcripts: interviews with women diplomats, State Department employees, undated; 1998-S-0057; 3.0 linear feet
  - Anne Armstrong interview: original transcript of with subject's handwritten corrections, undated; 1998-S-0057 (Box 1)
  - Jane Coon: original transcript with subject's handwritten corrections, undated; 1998-S-0057 (Box 1)
  - Ruth Farkas: original transcript with subject's handwritten corrections, undated; 1998-S-0057 (Box 1)
  - Millicent Fenwick: original transcript with subject's handwritten corrections, undated; 1998-S-0057 (Box 1)
  - Jeanne Kirkpatrick: original transcript with subject's handwritten corrections, undated; 1998-S-0057 (Box 1)
  - Betty Dillon: original transcript with subject's handwritten corrections, undated; 1998-S-0057 (Box 1)
  - Mabel Smythe: original transcript with subject's handwritten corrections, undated; 1998-S-0057 (Box 2)
  - Carol Laise: original transcript of oral history, undated; 1998-S-0057 (Box 2)
  - Margaret Tibbetts: original transcript with subject's handwritten corrections, undated; 1998-S-0057 (Box 2)
  - Rozanne Ridgeway: original transcript with subject's handwritten corrections, undated; 1998-S-0057 (Box 2)
  - Anne Martindell: original transcript with subject's handwritten corrections, undated; 1998-S-0057 (Box 2)
  - Constance Harvey: original transcript with subject's handwritten corrections, undated; 1998-S-0057 (Box 2)
  - Nancy Ostrander: original transcript with subject's handwritten corrections, undated; 1998-S-0057 (Box 3)
  - Mary Olmsted: original transcript with subject's handwritten corrections, undated; 1998-S-0057 (Box 3)
  - Personal effects of, materials regarding Frances Willis, undated; 1998-S-0057 (Box 3, Box 4)
  - Materials by chapter for history of women ambassadors; proposals to publishers, undated; 1998-S-0057 (Box 5)
  - Mari-Luci Jaramillo: final copy of oral history transcript, undated; 1998-S-0057 (Box 6)
  - Mabel Smythe: final copy of oral history transcript, undated; 1998-S-0057 (Box 6)
  - Betty Dillon: final copy of oral history transcript, undated; 1998-S-0057 (Box 6)
  - Ruth Farkas: final copy of oral history transcript, undated; 1998-S-0057 (Box 6)
  - Anne Martindell: final copy of oral history transcript, undated; 1998-S-0057 (Box 6)
  - Rozanne Ridgway: final copy of oral history transcript, undated; 1998-S-0057 (Box 6)
  - Printed, autographed copy, Ann Miller Morin's "Her Excellency: women ambassadors"; manuscript and related materials, undated; 1998-S-0057 (Box 6)
- Ann Miller Morin's oral histories of women ambassadors, correspondence, news clippings; case file, Alison Palmer v. State, undated; 1998-S-0058; 2.75 linear feet (3 boxes)
  - Corrected transcripts and other materials related to Mari-Luci Jaramillo, undated; 1998-S-0058 (Box 1)
  - Corrected transcripts and other materials related to Rosemary Ginn, undated; 1998-S-0058 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to Marquita Maytag, undated; 1998-S-0058 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to Nancy Rawls, undated; 1998-S-0058 (Box 1)
    Biographical / Historical
    Rawls died within six weeks from the start of the ambassadors' oral history project.
  - Materials related to Katherine White, undated; 1998-S-0058 (Box 1)
    White died within six-weeks of the onset of the ambassadors' oral history project.
  - Materials related to Patricia Harris, undated; 1998-S-0058 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to Perle Mesta, undated; 1998-S-0058 (Box 1)
  - Clippings and miscellaneous materials; subjects about women, 1985-1998; 1998-S-0058 (Box 2)
  - Materials pertaining to women's class action suit against Department of State, undated; 1998-S-0058 (Box 3)
- Ann Miller Morin's Women's Ambassador's Oral History project: transcripts, grant applications, correspondence, 1985-1987; undated; 1999-S-0017; 0.75 linear feet
  - Materials related to oral history of Anne Armstrong, undated; 1999-S-0017 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to oral history of Anne Cox Chambers, undated; 1999-S-0017 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to oral history of Jane Abell Coon, undated; 1999-S-0017
  - Materials related to oral history of Millicent Fenwick, undated; 1999-S-0017 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to oral history of Ambassador Rosemary Ginn, undated; 1999-S-0017 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to oral history of Consul General Constance Harvey, undated; 1999-S-0017 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to oral history of Ambassador Jeanne Kirkpatrick, undated; 1999-S-0017 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to oral history of Ambassador Carol Laise, undated; 1999-S-0017 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to oral history of Ambassador Clare Boothe Luce, undated; 1999-S-0017 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to oral history of Ambassador Mary Olmsted, undated; 1999-S-0017 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to oral history of Ambassador Nancy Ostrander, undated; 1999-S-0017 (Box 1)
  - Materials related to oral history of Ambassador Margaret Tibbetts, undated; 1999-S-0017 (Box 1)
  - Various requests, applications for funding, undated; 1999-S-0017 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence related to the Women Ambassadors' Oral History Project, 1985-1997; 1999-S-0017 (Box 1)